<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Judex expurgatorius: or, a short examination of the doctrine of purgatory, in a sermon upon 1 Pet.3.19. Together with an orthodoxall interpretation of the text. / By Am: Staveley, A.M.</title>
            <author>Staveley, Ambrose.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1655</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 49 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A93834</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S5345</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E850_2</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R207399</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99866453</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99866453</idno>
            <idno type="VID">118728</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A93834)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 118728)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 129:E850[2])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Judex expurgatorius: or, a short examination of the doctrine of purgatory, in a sermon upon 1 Pet.3.19. Together with an orthodoxall interpretation of the text. / By Am: Staveley, A.M.</title>
                  <author>Staveley, Ambrose.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 19, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J.G. for Rich: Lowndes, at the White-Lyon in S. Paul's Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1655.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed on page 4: Ambrose Stavely.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "July. 23".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Peter, 1st, III, 19 --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Purgatory --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:118728:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Judex Expurgatorius:</hi> OR, A SHORT EXAMINATION OF THE DOCTRINE OF PURGATORY, In a SERMON upon 1 PET. 3.19.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>TOGETHER WITH</hi> An Orthodoxall interpretation of the Text.</p>
            <p>By AM: STAVELEY, A.M.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>AUGUST:</bibl> 
               <hi>Scitote quia cum anima à corpore avellitur, ſtatim aut in Paradiſo pro meritis bonis collocatur, aut certè pro peccatis in inferni tartara praecipitatur.</hi>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>PSAL. 95.7.</hi>
               </bibl> To DAY if you will heare his voice, <hi>harden not your hearts.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>J. G.</hi> for RICH: LOWNDES, at the White-Lyon in S. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-yard, 1655.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:118728:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:118728:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT VVORSHIPFULL <hi>John Wroth</hi> and <hi>John Davies</hi> Eſquires.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>
               </hi> Have ſometimes peruſed, not without regret, that paſſage of the Hiſtorian, viz. <hi>Beneficia eo uſque laeta ſunt, dum videntur poſſe, ſolvi verum ubi multum ante venêre, pro gratiâ odium redditur.</hi> I muſt confeſſe my ſelfe conquered by accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulated civilities from you, and mine own inability to make you the leaſt recompenſe, for alas what are my endeavours? yet re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally not to belye mine own temper, I finde in my ſelfe an ambitious greadineſſe, to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace
<pb facs="tcp:118728:3"/>all occaſions, whereby I may ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe my gratitude towards you; wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe this ſmall Eſſay, whereunto I have took the boldneſse to prefixe your names, not to plead for my weakneſse, but to pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tronize my obedience, chuſing rather to run the hazard of (perhaps deſerved) cenſure, than not to make a publick ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgement of my many and deep en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagements for your abundant favours. Ac pt (I beſeech you) a thing born through the indulgence of Patronage, and in anſwer to your Commands, which I preſent as a teſtimony, how much greater my deſires, than my abilities are to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the ſtyle of being</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Gentlemen,</salute>
               <signed>Your obliged and obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient Servant, Ambroſe Stavely.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:118728:3"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>1 PET. 3.19.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. By which alſo he went and preached unto the Spirits in Priſon.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here are two Volumes propounded to us Men, wherein God readeth Divinity-Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures, and inſtructeth us in the glorious My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries concerning the eternall Power and Godhead: The <hi>Word of God,</hi> the <hi>Scriptures;</hi> and the <hi>Work of God,</hi> the <hi>Creation,</hi> are ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Tutors to the world below, teaching ſundry leſſons in rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the world above.</p>
            <p>And theſe two books ſo exactly parallel each the other in their ſtructure, frame, and conſtitution, that they cannot in reaſon but be looked upon as arguments of much ſtrength and conviction to prove that they were both caſt into the ſame mould, and the one came from the hand of the ſame workman with the other. The <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and temperature of the Scripture ſo proportionably anſwering the compoſition and modell of the Univerſe, is a great demonſtration, that one and the ſame hand was the Architect and contriver of them both: For as in the workes of God, we have high Mountaines in one place, and valleyes, and plains in another; flats and ſhallowes in one place, and heights and depths in another; ſome places altogether impregnable, and others againe eaſily acceſſible: We ſhall ſee the like Checker-wortk interwoven in the Word of God, and all beautifully conſpiring to render the Fabrick of them both, ſuitable to the wiſdome of him, who was their Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor and Artificer. The body of the Scripture is made up of depths and ſhallowes, of things neer at hand, and things a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>farre off; of things myſterious and profound, and things
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:118728:4"/>plain and obvious: There are contained in them ſome things whereof the weakeſt cannot likely be ignorant, and other things againe which the ſtrongeſt are not able to underſtand. God may be ſaid to dwell in the Scriptures, as in the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture he is ſaid to dwell. Sometimes he is ſaid to dwell in light, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.16. and elſewhere he is ſaid to dwell in dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 8 12. So in ſome paſſages of Scripture, God comes forth and ſhewes himſelfe in cleere and perfect beauty unto the world, as in a Viſion at noon day: Otherwhere he retires and hides himſelf behind the dark clouds of obſcure and difficult expreſsions, where we may ſeek him long, and not be able to finde him. In ſome veines and places of the Scripture, God ſits as it were, upon the very Superficies, &amp; Surface of the Letter, where even he who runs may read it; he ſpeaks plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly unto men, and ſpeaketh no parable at all; in others again he drawes the Curtaines between us and himſelfe, or deales with us as he did with <hi>Moſes;</hi> he puts us into the Cleft of the Rock, and covers us with his hand whilſt he paſſeth by. There is a path (ſaith <hi>Job</hi>) which no fowle hath known, neither hath the Vultures or the Kites eyes ſeen it, it is as yet hid from the eyes of all living, and kept cloſe from the fowles of the aire, <hi>Job</hi> 28.7. Men who ſoar aloft, and fly the higheſt pitch of reaſon, wiſdome and labour, yet fall ſhort in giving us a perfect account of the Divine meaning in ſeverall paſſages of the Scriptures. And amongſt the reſt this parcell of Holy writ, penned by Saint <hi>Peter,</hi> and <hi>[dictated]</hi> to me for this dayes employment (without any ſiniſter conſtruction be it ſpoken) is not the moſt inconſiderable, wherein <hi>God hath made dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe his ſecret place, his Pavilion round about are dark waters, and thick clouds of the skie,</hi> Pſal. 18.11.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Rabbins</hi> have a ſaying, there are four Keyes in Gods keeping: The key of the Clouds, the key of the Womb, the key of the Grave, and the key of Food. I may adde, that there is a fifth key in Gods beſtowing likewiſe, which is the key of the Scriptures; and when we attempt to ſearch into thoſe <hi>Arcana Dei,</hi> we had need to pray that God would deale with us, as he did with the Apoſtles, <hi>To open our underſtanding, that we may underſtand the Scriptures,</hi> Luke 24.45. Since it
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:118728:4"/>is <hi>He alone who hath the key of</hi> David, <hi>that openeth, and no man ſhutteth, that ſhutteth and no man openeth,</hi> Rev. 3.7.</p>
            <p>I ſpeake it not to monopolize any vaine applauſe to my ſelf (for I finde not in me the leaſt temptation or itching deſire after oſtentation) neither yet to diſcourage my ſelfe from a modeſt, reverend ſcrutiny into the meaning; but there is ſcarce a Text of greater difficulty, whereon more various, and divers expoſitions are faſtned; ſo that I may take up the ſame language of Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> though uttered upon another caſe, <hi>Speak I theſe things of my ſelfe, or doe not others ſay the ſame alſo?</hi> Saint <hi>Auſtin</hi> being conſulted by <hi>Evodius</hi> about the meaning of the place, confeſſeth it did exceedingly puzzle him, and that he durſt not affirme any thing about it: Will you heare him in his owne Dialect? <hi>Quaeſtio</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>quam mihi propoſuiſti, ex Epiſtolâ Apoſtoli Petri, ſolet nos (ut te non latere arbitror) vehementiſſime commovere.</hi> And again, <hi>Vides quam latebroſum ſit, &amp; quae me moveant, ne affirmare hinc aliquid audeam:</hi> And the Jeſuite <hi>Lorinus</hi> in his Commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary upon it, calls it, <hi>Difficilimum locum,</hi> a moſt difficult place, and rehearſeth ten ſeverall expoſitions. And ſo <hi>Eſtius</hi> alſo upon the place ſaith, <hi>Locus hic omnium penè interpretum judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cio difficilimus varieque expoſitus, &amp;c.</hi> This place, in the judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of almoſt all Interpreters, is moſt difficult, and is ſo di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſly expounded, that <hi>Lorinus</hi> reckons up nine interpretati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of it, to which he addes his owne for the tenth, and yet hath not touched all neither. And both <hi>Eſtius</hi> and <hi>Lorinus</hi> note, that onely <hi>Arias Montanus</hi> did think the place eaſie to be underſtood, but withall his expoſition of it is ſuch, that o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers will not eaſily embrace it. For as they relate, <hi>Arias</hi> by the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, by the Spirits in Priſon, doth un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand thoſe eight perſons ſhut up in the Arke, which was a priſon to them: <hi>Bellarmine</hi> alſo upon occaſion of the Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie, about <hi>Limbus Patrum,</hi> and Chriſts deſcention into Hell, treating of this place ſpeaks thus; <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t autem hic locus qui ſemper obſcuriſſimus habitus intelligatur.</hi> So that <hi>è confeſſo</hi> on all ſides, this place hath been accounted moſt obſcure: One ſenſe pleaſeth <hi>Origen,</hi> it diſlikes another; <hi>Hillary</hi> approves one Paraphraſe, another rejects it; <hi>Zwinglius</hi> and <hi>Aretius</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:118728:5"/>concurre in one opinion, there are more oppoſe it than ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe unto it. <hi>Calvin</hi> and his followers would have their meaning take place, and others no leſſe eminent in judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and learning refell it. I ſhould exceed the bounds of Diſcourſe, ſhould I preſent you with each particular mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, together with what is requiſite to be delivered in the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mainder.</p>
            <p>In ſuch a Sea of Controverſies, and variety of Expoſitions, I confeſſe my ſelfe ſometimes almoſt at a loſſe, when I would reſolve where to begin, &amp; what method to proſecute for your preſent entertainment. But to avoide prolixity, there are onely two I meet with which are moſt conſiderable; the former is that of the <hi>Romiſh Church,</hi> who thus comment upon theſe words, that <hi>Chriſt</hi> did free thoſe antient Fathers from <hi>Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory,</hi> wherein they remained impriſoned till at, or by his death, he paid their ranſome, and ſatisfied his Fathers juſtice. But this gloſſe of theirs being founded upon a falſe Hypothe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis, is deſervedly rejected as ſpurious and fictitious: but me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinkes I heare ſome ſay, how? is it founded upon a falſe Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potheſis? <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, it is eaſie to create an adverſary in a mans fancy, and afterwards foile him at pleaſure; this ſounds to the eare, but doth not ſatisfie the judgement. In examination therefore of this quarrel between us, I ſhall deal <hi>fide Romanâ, &amp; fide Anti-Romanâ:</hi> with a Roman faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, but an Anti-Roman Faith.</p>
            <p>The nature of a channell is beſt diſcovered by retiring back to the fountaine, and it will not be a little conducible to our purpoſe, ot enquire after the Authors, who firſt laid the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of this opinion, and how, and in what manner, in after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times it gathered ſo much ſtrength, that to keep fuell at Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory-fire, it hath put all Chriſtendome into a Paroxiſme, and inflamed the whole world in an unextinguiſhable confla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gration.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Chemnitius</hi> a learned Author, who gives us the Narration, or if you pleaſe, the Hiſtory of Purgatory, tells us that he findes <hi>Plato,</hi> who flouriſhed about 400 years before Chriſts incarnation, to be the firſt who laid the ſtructure of Purgato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry; and afterwards, when the <hi>Platonick Philoſophers</hi> began to
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:118728:5"/>be in admiration with the <hi>Eccleſiaſticall Doctors,</hi> this <hi>Theſis</hi> of his had ſo much liberty, as to be controverted in the <hi>Church.</hi> Now nothing elſe but humane Inference, and Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophical ratiocination inclined <hi>Plato</hi> to broach this opinion; <hi>Euſebius</hi> in his book, <hi>De praeparatione Evangelica,</hi> having tranſcribed a large diſpute of <hi>Plato,</hi> out of his <hi>Tractat. de Anima,</hi> in reference to a future life, informeth us, that <hi>Plato</hi> believed, that ſuch men who ſeemed <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>inſanabiles eſſe,</hi> to be incurable (as ſuch who committed murder praeme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditately, or the like) were caſt into a place of torment, from whence they never were to be ſet at liberty. Such who com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted great ſinnes, but were <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Medicabilia,</hi> crimes curable (as if out of ſodaine paſſion, they committed Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlaughter, or ſuch like) but yet ſpent the reſt of their life, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, in ſorrow and repentance; they propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionably to their crimes were caſt into flames, but of a diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent nature from the former, and after a yeares expiration in ſufferance, approached to the Lake <hi>Acheruſias,</hi> where they im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plored mercy from him whom they had offended: And if they would intreat their Adverſary to be reconciled, they were free, otherwiſe there to remain till they had ſued out their pardon. On the other ſide ſuch who lived tranſcendently pious, aſcend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to a place of bliſs, there to reſide without diſturbance: Thoſe whoſe converſations in this world were of a different nature, neither reaching to a full meaſure of perfection, nor tending to downe-right profaneneſſe paſſed by <hi>Acheron</hi> into a Lake of Fire, and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, being purged, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, are abſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, and afterwards receive a remuneration for their good deeds: Thus <hi>Plato.</hi> And it is obſervable that when <hi>Euſebius</hi> relates ſome opinions of <hi>Plato,</hi> and that purpoſely too, to ſhew Philoſophers held ſome tenents not diſſonant from the doctrine of the Church, he makes mention of two places one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for the dead, as agreeable to Scripture, adding nothing of a third place, or of Purgatory, which queſtionleſſe he would not there have admitted had the doctrine of Purgatory then been known or received in the Church: And Saint <hi>Auſtin</hi> does not diſſemble it in his booke, <hi>De civitate Dei;</hi> that puniſhment in Purgatory after death, was the poſition of
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:118728:6"/>
               <hi>Platonick Phyloſophers,</hi> and the ſame Saint <hi>Auſtin</hi> rehearſing that verſe of <hi>Virgil,</hi>
               <q>Quique ſui memores alios fecêre merendo,</q> wonders to meet with ſuch an opinion in the Poet, that the dead received comfort by the merits and ſuffrages of the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving; adding moreover, that without any authority of Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture this <hi>Theſis</hi> crept from the Schoole of <hi>Plato</hi> into the Church of God.</p>
            <p>I ſhould treſpaſſe too much upon your patience to enlarge my ſelf in this particular; but if I doe not too much flatter my ſelf, nor too fondly indulge mine own credulity, I have alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy produced enough to clear it, that <hi>Pontificiall Purgatory</hi> received its Originall light from <hi>Plato</hi>'s dim <hi>lampe;</hi> So that <hi>Tertullian</hi> upon mature deliberation pronounceth, <hi>Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phos eſſe Hareticorum Patriarchas,</hi> that Philoſophers were the Patriarks of Hereticks. Thus backed by no other authority, did this doctrine at firſt advance it ſelfe into the world, when the <hi>Jewes</hi> being mingled with the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> learned their work as the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> ſpeaketh: For the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> ſeeing how <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens</hi> expreſſed their <hi>Philoſtorgie,</hi> and naturall affections to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards their dead friends, in ſuperſtitious Sacrifices and Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quies, this practiſe begun in the declining of <hi>Judaiſme</hi> to take place amongſt them. And on that account, after the time of the <hi>Prophets,</hi> the <hi>Jewes</hi> introduced <hi>Prayers</hi> and <hi>Sacrifices</hi> for the <hi>Dead;</hi> about 170. yeares before <hi>Chriſts Incarnation;</hi> the firſt Preſident and Example whereof we meet with, is the 2 of <hi>Macchabees</hi> 12. with which book whoſoever is acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, ſhall finde the whole frame and fabrick of the <hi>Jewiſh Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment</hi> perturbed and diſordered, the face of it, both as to <hi>Eccleſiaſticall</hi> and <hi>Civill relations</hi> quite changed: <hi>Iſrael</hi> had loſt her former beauty wherewith ſhe was renowned, and the whole ſtate of affaires depraved and corrupted; Their <hi>Empire</hi> ruinous, their <hi>Doctrine</hi> unſound, their <hi>Manners,</hi> their <hi>Rites,</hi> their <hi>Langnage,</hi> their <hi>Names</hi> all extinguiſhed, and in one word, in affection of conformity with two other Nations, they were wholly degenerated into <hi>Heatheniſme.</hi> No war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantable
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:118728:6"/>rantable Preſident or Example had they, no precept, no pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe encouraging this action of theirs, onely what them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves had copied forth from the cuſtome of thoſe <hi>Gentiles,</hi> amongſt whom they had their converſation; whereas neither in the books of <hi>Moſes,</hi> (which are, as I may ſo terme them, the <hi>Head-Quarters</hi> of the <hi>Scriptures</hi>) nor yet in the <hi>Prophets,</hi> we ſhall not finde the leaſt ſyllable, tending to advantage their opinion or practiſe, nor doe the <hi>Romaniſts</hi> themſelves ſtick to aſſent to us in this Poſition: And ſhould I tell you, that thoſe books of the <hi>Macchabees</hi> are not <hi>Canonicall,</hi> and by conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, no infallible ſtandards for <hi>Speculative</hi> or <hi>Practicall Theologie,</hi> it is no more than what I am able to juſtifie, having the ſuffrages of learned and judicious Authors, corrobo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rating this aſſertion; To omit <hi>Lyranus,</hi> who ſayes, <hi>Non ſunt in Canone, leguntur tamen per conſtitutionem Eccleſiae Romanae:</hi> But withall, <hi>ut ſobrie legantur.</hi> S. <hi>Auſtin</hi> in his ſecond Book <hi>De Doctrinâ Chriſtianâ,</hi> Chap. 8. reckoning up the Books ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted Canonicall, omitteth theſe books of <hi>Macchabees</hi> in his Catalogue, ſo that it ſeems that learned Father eſteemed them <hi>Apochryphall.</hi> And Saint <hi>Jerome</hi> ſaith expreſly, <hi>Legit haec ad aedificationem plebis, non autem ad authoritatem Eccleſiaſtico<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum dogmatum confirmandam.</hi> The Church reads them indeed for inſtruction of the People, but not to confirme any <hi>Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticall Tenent;</hi> moreover adding, <hi>Eorum quippe authoritas, ad roboranda ea quae in contentionem veniunt, minus idonea ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicantur.</hi> Their Authority is inſufficient to decide a <hi>Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie.</hi> To this agreeth Saint <hi>Cyprian, Lege quidem in Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſia, volui non tamen proferri ad authoritatem ex his fidei confirmandam.</hi> This now was the ſenſe of the antient Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</p>
            <p>I might expatiate my diſcourſe, to ſhew the vaſt difference in manner of compoſing thoſe two books, the <hi>Genius</hi> running through the veines of the one, being altogether unlike that of the other: But he whoſoever was the <hi>Amanuenſis</hi> of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond book, hath given occaſion enough to ſuſpect it, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledging he had Epitomized it into one volume, from the works of one <hi>Jaſon</hi> of <hi>Cyrene,</hi> who had degeſted the Hiſtory in five books, as in 2 <hi>Macehabees</hi> 2.23. you may at lei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:118728:7"/>peruſe, which place, when you conſult, be pleaſed to take a view of that ſlender, and childiſh Apologie, made at the end of the Story, which ſcarce reliſheth of a <hi>maſculine temper,</hi> much leſſe of a <hi>Divine inspiration;</hi> 2 <hi>Macchabees</hi> 14. <hi>ver.</hi> 38, 39. And it is not unworthy of our obſervation, that in all Hiſtories it cannot be proved; after the time of <hi>Maccha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baeus</hi> till our <hi>Saviours</hi> dayes, that this cuſtome of <hi>Sacrificing</hi> or <hi>Praying</hi> for the <hi>Dead,</hi> was retained or uſed amongſt the <hi>Jewes:</hi> Indeed the <hi>Rabbins</hi> after <hi>Chriſts</hi> time, having their eyes blinded, and their hearts hardned, renewed it afreſh, and (<hi>Lyranus</hi> relating it) as from the example of <hi>Razis</hi> killing himſelfe, they counted it an Act meritorious, to be <hi>felones de ſe,</hi> their owne Executioners; ſo from the practiſe of <hi>Mac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chabaeus,</hi> the <hi>Rabbins</hi> inſtituted <hi>Memorialls</hi> for the <hi>Dead:</hi> And to this day in their <hi>Synagogues,</hi> they have <hi>Memoriales Libellos,</hi> out of which twice every yeare, from their Pulpits, publickly they rehearſe the names of the deceaſed: And at the cloſe, prayer is made, that <hi>God</hi> would in mercy remember their <hi>Souls</hi> and place them in <hi>Paradiſe,</hi> with <hi>Abraham, Iſaac</hi> and <hi>Jacob.</hi> Thus have I dealt impartially in this <hi>Hiſtory,</hi> which how much, or how little it patronizeth <hi>Roman Purgatory,</hi> I leave it to the arbitration of any indifferent Judge; and whereas our adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries confeſſe, that they cannot produce any other place ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king plainly to ſtrengthen their Doctrine; manifeſt is it, how ruinous is their ſtructure, whoſe very baſis and foundation is ſo infirme and tottering. Having now cleered it, that the <hi>Aca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demies</hi> of the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> were the <hi>Seminaries</hi> of this opinion of <hi>Purgatory,</hi> teaching it the <hi>Jewes,</hi> when their <hi>Religion</hi> was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caying under the <hi>Law;</hi> it now remaineth to be treated, how it had its entrance amongſt <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> under the time of the <hi>Gospell:</hi> That <hi>Chriſt</hi> and his <hi>Apoſtles</hi> propounded no ſuch <hi>Doctrine,</hi> might be inſiſted on, did not the time prevent me. But if we examine the Spring-head of it, whence firſt it did deſcend, we ſhall finde the occaſion of its Introduction into <hi>Chriſtian Churches,</hi> was no more warrantable, than of old into the <hi>Jewiſh,</hi> both of them alike invalid: I can now ſtand but onely to preſent you with a ſhort view of it, which in briefe was this; Preſently after the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> were taken out of the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:118728:7"/>world, there went abroad ſome <hi>Apocryphall Comments</hi> under their names, which being diſſipated, began to be obtruded, if not to be believed, yet to be diſputed, and in proceſſe of time, gathered ſtrength under the arrogated title of <hi>Apoſtoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Tradition:</hi> Amongſt the reſt, one <hi>Hermas,</hi> whom report maketh to be Saint <hi>Paul</hi>'s Scholar, and he onely averreth it as being dictated to him from the viſion of an old woman, where the relation is ſo weak and ridiculous, that it is beneath ſeriouſneſſe to repeate it: Whereupon <hi>Chemnitius</hi> maketh this Animadverſion, <hi>Et haec lector benè notet quod: Purgatori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um quando ſub novo Teſtamento primum quaſi de longè emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>care caepit anile commentum ab anu perſonula profectum fuit.</hi> I ſhall not need to Engliſh it. The like ſpurious ſtuffe is Father<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on Saint <hi>James,</hi> and Saint <hi>Andrew,</hi> to the former where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, is imputed a <hi>Maſſe,</hi> wherein is contained prayer for the <hi>Dead,</hi> and a nameleſſe <hi>Author,</hi> penning a book of the <hi>Acts of the Apoſtles,</hi> mentioneth, that S. <hi>Andrew</hi> interceded for an old dead Man: And <hi>Irenaeus</hi> writeth that there were ſome <hi>Hereticks</hi> in his time, who pouring Oyle and Water with ſome certain invocations, upon the head of the deceaſed, thought thereby they mitigated their paines, if any were inflicted upon them, I ſhould be too prodigall of my time, in purſuing the ſeries of the <hi>Hiſtory,</hi> how <hi>Clemens Alexandrinus</hi> and <hi>Origen</hi> were ſomewhat tainted with an opinion concerning <hi>Purgato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> but ſo, that it was quite of a different nature from that which the <hi>Romaniſts</hi> endeavour to propagate; For <hi>Origen</hi>'s <hi>Purgatory</hi> admitteth no eaſe, relaxation or redemption, by the prayers or workes of the living, but that every one expi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ateth for himſelfe, and therefore indebted to none but them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves for their releaſement. And <hi>Clemens Alexandrinus</hi> affirmeth it very dubiouſly, (if we may give credit to <hi>Chem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitius</hi>) who onely ſayes, <hi>Forſan ceſſabunt ſupplicia poſt hanc vitam;</hi> So that at beſt his is but conjectural, and (it may be) this in ſucceeding generations, was controverted in the <hi>Church,</hi> till the <hi>Grecians</hi> ſeeing how apt ſuch diſputes were to concili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate ſecret approbation, in a Councell about the yeare 550. by publick authority exploded it, ſo that never after did the <hi>Ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtern Churches</hi> receive it, untill about the yeare 1430. <hi>Greece</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:118728:8"/>being infeſted by the attempts of the <hi>Turkes,</hi> in hopes to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure aſſiſtance. <hi>Paleologus</hi> Emperour of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured to make up the breach between them and the <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tines:</hi> To which purpoſe at <hi>Ferrara</hi> and <hi>Florens</hi> Agents met on both ſides, to compoſe the difference, where the great Controverſie betwixt the <hi>Eaſtern</hi> and <hi>Weſterne</hi> Churches, concerning <hi>The Proceſſion of the Holy Ghoſt,</hi> was fully diſcuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and deſided, but their concurrence in this was not ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory to the full; the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> preſſeth ſtrongly, that amongſt the reſt of the <hi>Articles</hi> of <hi>Faith,</hi> there ſhould be a ſubſcription likewiſe to <hi>Puratory,</hi> to the Supremacy of the <hi>Roman See,</hi> and to Tranſubſtantiation in the <hi>Euchariſt:</hi> The <hi>Grecians</hi> reply, their Commiſſion extended no further than to treat with them, concerning the <hi>Proceſſion</hi> of the <hi>holy Ghoſt,</hi> &amp; as for any other Queſtions newly ſtated, they could come to no poſitive determination, without licenſe from the <hi>Eaſterne Churches:</hi> If <hi>Greece</hi> will withdraw her hand from ſubſcribing, <hi>Rome</hi> is reſolved to hold her hand in furniſhing them with <hi>Auxiliary ſupplyes:</hi> At laſt neceſſity tyrannizing upon <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leologus,</hi> they are forced to joyne with <hi>Rome,</hi> which accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly was done in the yeare, 1439. but ſcarce were 14. years expired, <hi>viz.</hi> in the yeare 1453. when behold <hi>Mahumet</hi> Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour of the <hi>Turks</hi> ſurprizeth <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> and with a pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſſant Army, invading the <hi>Grecian</hi> Territories, ſubdues all the <hi>Eaſtern Empire</hi> to his Dominions, which ſad and Tragicall paſſage the <hi>Grecians</hi> interpreted as the effects of a juſt judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment from Heaven upon them, perſecuting them for their baſe diſſembled compliance with the <hi>Latins,</hi> and therefore broke off all league and familiarity with them, and as for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly, ſo to this day conſtantly and ſtoutly renounce and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claim <hi>Purgatory,</hi> reſolving rather to ſuffer ſlavery under the <hi>Turks,</hi> where they enjoy their <hi>Religion,</hi> than ſubmit themſelves to the unbounded, unlimited, uſurped juriſdiction of the <hi>Roman Patriarch.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In ſum, therefore (for I take no delight in <hi>Polemical Diſcourſes</hi>) <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, Old womens Fables, Apparitions, &amp; Spectrums of the dead, conſultation with, and anſwers from Deviliſh and Heatheniſh Oracles, theſe at firſt created <hi>Purgatory</hi> for <hi>Orthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dox
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:118728:8"/>Divinity,</hi> which <hi>Rome</hi> muſt now ſtickle to uphold, eſpecially ſince the revenues coming in thereby warms her Biſhops <hi>Kit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chin,</hi> &amp; if <hi>fame</hi> belies him not, provides him his ſecond Courſe. I am now ſenſible, that by reaſon of the ſtraitneſſe of the time, I muſt neceſſarily retract my firſt reſolutions when I propounded to my ſelf the method in handling this branch of holy Writ, which was then to have alleadged the <hi>Latine Fathers,</hi> where I finde ſome affirming <hi>Purgatory,</hi> others re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining <hi>Scepticks</hi> in their judgements, ſuſpending their Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicts either <hi>Pro</hi> or <hi>Con,</hi> others againe down-right denying it: As for citations of Councels, themſelves have given me occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion enough to ſpare that labour, not denying but that the four firſt <hi>Generall</hi> ones were ignorant of <hi>Purgatory,</hi> nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was its doctrine ratified by any other antient one till that of <hi>Florence</hi> celebrated in the yeare 1439. where the <hi>Gracians</hi> reduced to <hi>Exigencies</hi> were compelled to aſſent, though af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards they did <hi>Palinodiam canere,</hi> repenting themſelves of their cowardly <hi>Pacification,</hi> as hath already been ſpoken. If the Councell of <hi>Trent</hi> be further alledged againſt us, the whole world hath had ſufficient notice of thoſe juglings, impoſtures and bribings of ſuffrages uſed in their proceedings, we can therefore without much aſtoniſhment, heare their <hi>Anathema</hi>'s thundring againſt us, whileſt we heare God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe pronouncing, <hi>That if we or an Angell from Heaven preach any other Gospell, let him be accurſed, Gal.</hi> 1.8. But to what purpoſe ſhould I fight a duell with a Cloud, when by our lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Adverſaries acknowledging the difficulty of the Text, and the rehearſall of the variety of ſences, whereof it is capable; thus much is obtained, that the words have not in them ſuch an undeniable, unqueſtionable meaning, as to promote <hi>Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory,</hi> but that other expoſitions may reaſonably be inferred from them.</p>
            <p>The ſecond interpretation I meet with, be pleaſed to take with this ſhort <hi>Paraphraſe;</hi> that Chriſt from the beginning being <hi>Head</hi> and <hi>Governor</hi> of the Church, came in the dayes of <hi>Noah,</hi> not in Body, which then he had not, but in Spirit, and preached by the mouth of <hi>Noah,</hi> for the ſpace of 120. yeares, to the diſobedient, which would not repent, and
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:118728:9"/>therefore are now in Priſon reſerved to the laſt judgment: Thus <hi>Beza.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now I am the more willingly inclinable to embrace this ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, becauſe (beſides the agreeableneſſe it hath with the precedent and conſequent verſes) S. <hi>Auſtin</hi> in his fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned Epiſtle to <hi>Evodius</hi> renders it, if not in the ſame words, yet in effect to the ſame ſenſe: By the ſpirits in <hi>Priſon</hi> he conceived to be meant men that lived in the dayes of <hi>Noah,</hi> whoſe ſoules were in their mortall bodies as in priſons, to which men <hi>Chriſt</hi> in his Spirit by <hi>Noah</hi> preached, though ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſſe they would not believe: <hi>Bellarmine</hi> and <hi>Eſtius</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge this to have been the opinion of Saint <hi>Aug.</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning theſe words of Saint <hi>Peter,</hi> and that it concurreth very nigh with <hi>Beza's</hi> expoſition.</p>
            <p>This interpretation is embraced not only by <hi>Bede</hi> whom <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larmine</hi> mentions here in following Saint <hi>Aug:</hi> but alſo by <hi>Aquinas,</hi> and others, as <hi>Eſtius</hi> obſerveth, who alſo addeth that <hi>Heſſelius</hi> (a <hi>Romiſh</hi> Authour) doth underſtand the place much after the ſame manner: And as <hi>Lorinus</hi> relateth <hi>Diegus Paiva</hi> one who wrote in defence of the Councell of <hi>Trent</hi> doth directly expouned the words as <hi>Beza</hi> doth, though he would not have it thought that <hi>Paiva</hi> received it from <hi>Beza.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But againſt this interpretation it may perhaps be objected, that the <hi>Spirit</hi> by which <hi>Chriſt</hi> went and preached to the <hi>Spirits</hi> in <hi>Priſon,</hi> is oppoſed to the <hi>Fleſh,</hi> and muſt therefore ſignifie <hi>Chriſts Soule,</hi> not his <hi>Divine Nature.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I anſwer, that <hi>Chriſts Divine Nature</hi> is moſt fitly under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood by the word <hi>Spirit,</hi> even as by the word <hi>Fleſh,</hi> is to be underſtood, not onely his <hi>Body,</hi> but his whole <hi>Humane Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture:</hi> in reſpect of which <hi>Nature,</hi> Chriſt was put to death, and was quickned by his <hi>Divine Nature:</hi> Thus <hi>Oecumenius</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounds it, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; put to death in the Nature of the <hi>Fleſh,</hi> that is, <hi>Humane Nature,</hi> and raiſed againe by the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of the <hi>Divine Nature,</hi> by which he went and preached, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And why ſhould this <hi>Expoſition</hi> ſeem ſtrange, when as <hi>Fleſh</hi> is put for <hi>Chriſts Humane Nature,</hi> and therefore on the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſide, the word <hi>Spirit</hi> may denote his <hi>Divine Nature?</hi>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:118728:9"/>But againe it may be objected, that Saint <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith, <hi>Chriſt [went] and preached,</hi> &amp;c. Therefore it is meant of the <hi>Soule,</hi> not of his <hi>Divine Nature,</hi> in which reſpect it cannot be ſaid, but improperly, <hi>Chriſt [went] and preached.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I anſwer, there is no neceſſity to take it properly in the words of Saint <hi>Peter,</hi> more than in the words of Saint <hi>Paul, Epheſ.</hi> 2.17. When he ſaith <hi>Chriſt came and preached peace un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Epheſians,</hi> which muſt be meant of <hi>Chriſt</hi> coming and preaching by the <hi>Apoſtle,</hi> for otherwiſe he in his owne perſon did not preach unto them. And thus <hi>Eſtius</hi> notes it to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded by S. <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> the interlineary gloſſe, <hi>Aquinas, Lyra</hi> and <hi>Cajetan:</hi> it is objected again, that by <hi>Spirits</hi> in <hi>Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> cannot be underſtood <hi>Living Men,</hi> except Saint <hi>Peter</hi> ſhould on purpoſe ſpeak improperly, and obſcurely.</p>
            <p>I anſwer, not <hi>Living Men,</hi> but the <hi>Soules</hi> of Men ſeparated from their <hi>Bodies,</hi> are termed <hi>Spirits</hi> in <hi>priſon,</hi> as being in the <hi>Priſon</hi> of <hi>Hell,</hi> when <hi>Peter</hi> wrote of them, though they were not ſo, but were joyned to their <hi>Bodies,</hi> and ſo both <hi>Soules</hi> and <hi>Bodies</hi> joyned together, were living men, when <hi>Chriſt</hi> preached unto them by the mouth of <hi>Noah.</hi> For the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Spirits</hi> in <hi>Priſon</hi> or <hi>Cuſtody,</hi> [<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>] ſignifying any kind of receptacle, <hi>Rev.</hi> 18.2. are thoſe <hi>Soules</hi> of Men that lay ſo ſheathed, ſo uſeleſſe and unprofitable in their <hi>Bodies,</hi> immerſed ſo deep in carnality, as not to performe any ſervice to <hi>God,</hi> who inſpired and placed them there, and 'tis elſewhere a figurative ſpeech, to expreſſe wicked men, who are called <hi>Priſoners</hi> and in <hi>Priſon,</hi> that is, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; <hi>Iſa.</hi> 42.7. and <hi>Iſa.</hi> 49.9. and bound in <hi>Priſon, Iſa.</hi> 61.1. to theſe <hi>Chriſt,</hi> that is, <hi>God eternall, who was yeſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day, and to day, and forever,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> went and preached, in or by that <hi>Spirit,</hi> not perſonally, but by <hi>Noah</hi> the <hi>Preacher</hi> of <hi>Righteouſneſſe,</hi> to the old world, by whom he gave thoſe treatable warnings, to them who made no uſe of the light of <hi>Nature,</hi> premoniſhing them of that <hi>Deluge</hi> of <hi>wrath,</hi> which <hi>God</hi> was preparing againſt <hi>impenitent</hi> and <hi>obdurate ſinners.</hi> Taking this to be the true and genuine meaning of the words, (for you will much aſſiſt my modeſty, if you pleaſe to call it ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction)
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:118728:10"/>there naturally arifeth this enſuing Corol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lary. That</p>
            <p>
               <hi>God,</hi> before he proceedeth in judgement againſt a <hi>People,</hi> giveth ſome <hi>ſignall premonitions,</hi> to forewarne them of their intended ruine.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Chriſt</hi> here by his <hi>Spirit</hi> went and preached to the <hi>Old world,</hi> before he brought upon them the <hi>Deluge,</hi> and inundation of waters: <hi>God</hi> is not in this caſe like the <hi>Cannon,</hi> which firſt Executes, and then Reports, but he firſt makes the Report, that afterwards there may be no need of the <hi>Execution. God</hi> needed not to have given theſe men any warning of his <hi>judgment,</hi> they gave him no warning of their <hi>ſinne,</hi> no reſpit: Yet that he might approve his mercies to the very wicked, he gives them one hundred and twenty yeares reſpite of repent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. How loath is he to ſtrike, who threats and treats ſo fruitleſly, ſo ineffectually? Had he delighted in revenge, how ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily, how juſtly might he have ſurprized them unawares? where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as giving them warning, it was a ſign he deſired to be prevent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: The ſame Method doth he obſerve towards <hi>Sodom,</hi> diſplay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his white flag of <hi>Mercy,</hi> before he hung forth his black flagge of <hi>Defiance;</hi> juſt <hi>Lot</hi> warneth them like a <hi>Prophet,</hi> ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſeth them as a <hi>Father: Nineveh</hi> had <hi>Jonah</hi> diſpatched to her, to ſtand <hi>Sentinell, yet within forty dayes, and Nineveh ſhall be deſtroyed.</hi> Nor was <hi>Iſrael</hi> exempted, from being par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taker of this royall favour: <hi>God</hi> ſent his Prophets to warn her to <hi>repentance, Judges</hi> 6.1. And he ſent them <hi>Prophets to bring them back again to the Lord,</hi> 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 24.19. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſaith Saint <hi>Chryſoſtome.</hi> He foretelleth what he will bring upon us, for this end, that he may not bring it upon us, and warneth before he ſtriketh, to make us carefull to avoid the ſtroke: Peruſe all the <hi>Prophets</hi> of <hi>God</hi> in former dayes, employed for <hi>Iſrael</hi>'s reducement, and we ſhall finde <hi>Promiſes</hi> mixt with <hi>threats,</hi> and ſtill, <hi>Thus ſaith the Lord,</hi> or, <hi>The word of the Lord came unto me,</hi> is prefixed in the Fronteſpiece of all their <hi>Embaſſies.</hi> She had her ſedulous watchment ſtanding upon the top of her <hi>Towers,</hi> ſtriking up <hi>Alarums</hi> at the approach of dangers. Nor doth he onely premoniſh by the voice of his
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:118728:10"/>word, but his workes likewiſe have oftentimes a language in them, calling upon men to provide for their ſafety and ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity: <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> may bear me witneſſe in this particular: The prodigious <hi>Earthquakes,</hi> the <hi>portentous Eclipſe</hi> of the <hi>Sun,</hi> the <hi>Comet</hi> like a <hi>flaming Sword</hi> hanging over the <hi>City,</hi> and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuing a yeare, the great <hi>Light</hi> ſhining about the <hi>Altar,</hi> and the <hi>Temple,</hi> about nine a clock of the night, upon the <hi>Feaſt of unleavened bread,</hi> the <hi>Meteors</hi> ſeen through all her <hi>Regions;</hi> the apparation in the <hi>clouds,</hi> of <hi>Chariots</hi> and <hi>troops,</hi> of armed men encompaſſing her walls, and many ſuch things of the like nature, <hi>Euſebius</hi> calls them, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and againe, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Prodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gies</hi> and <hi>Sermons</hi> of God himſelfe, manifeſtly fore-ſignifying the approaching deſolation: Thus <hi>God</hi> diſchargeth theſe warning-pieces over our heads, before he gives fire to the Murdering-pieces at our Hearts, and in briefe, theſe three en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuing <hi>Reaſons</hi> may be given:
<list>
                  <item>1. <hi>Ad benevolentiam indicandam.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>Ad apologiam tollendam.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. <hi>Ad vindictam acuendam.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Ad benevolentiam indicandam,</hi> to declare his loving kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to the Sons of Men, <hi>God who is rich in Mercy, Eph.</hi> 2.4. and delighteth to be ſtiled the <hi>God of Mercies, Nehem.</hi> 9.31. and the <hi>Father of Merciet,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.3. abundantly manifeſteth his mercy in dealing thus graciouſly, in giving ſuch timely notice of his approaching judgement, and therefore is it he that doth <hi>arripere anſam,</hi> take all advantages as it were, and lay hold on all occaſions to doe good, but to puniſh and take vengeance is <hi>opus alienum,</hi> as ſome expound that in <hi>Iſa.</hi> 28. His ſtrange worke, his ſtrange act, an employment wherein he taketh no delight: <hi>As I live, ſaith the Lord, I have no pleaſure in the death of the wicked.</hi> Hence proceed thoſe debatements, thoſe rowlings and ſoundings of bowells, thoſe yearnings within him to ſhew compaſſion, as if it were poſſible he could, he would reconcile his <hi>Juſtice</hi> and <hi>Mercy,</hi> to be <hi>Juſt</hi> to the <hi>Sinne,</hi> and yet be <hi>Mercifull</hi> to the <hi>Sinner: O Ephraim what ſhall I doe unto thee? O Judah how ſhall I entreat thee? and
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:118728:11"/>why will yo dye O houſe of Iſrael?</hi> Theſe are the Expoſtulations God uſeth with men, whereby they may diſcerne how they have provoked an unwilling inflicter: Vengeance cometh on heavily, and drawes a ſigh from God, when he is neceſſitated to prepare his Rodde, to unſheath his Sword, to bend his Bow, and make ready his Quiver: <hi>Heu conſolabor! Ah I muſt, I ſee there is no remedy, eaſe me of mine Adverſaries, and avenge me of mine Enemies. Slow to anger, and loath to ſtrike.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>Quique dolet quoties cogitur eſſe ferox.</q>
            <p>But gracious and mercifull, and of great kindneſſe, abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant in Truth, <hi>Joel</hi> 2.13. which is the firſt reaſon aſſigned for our Doctrine.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Ad Apologiam tollendam,</hi> to cut off all manner of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe, to elide all their Apologies, to evacuate all the evaſions which the wits of men are apt to frame and contrive in their owne behalfe. <hi>If I had not come and ſpoke unto them</hi> (ſaith our Saviour) <hi>they had not had ſinne, but now they have no cloak for their ſinne, John</hi> 15.22. Here is that which ſhall ſtop the mouthes of all prophane men, that neither would <hi>Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> drive them, nor <hi>Mercies</hi> draw them to repentance. <hi>Whoſoever heareth the ſound of the Trumpet, and taketh no war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, his blood ſhall be upon him: Ezek.</hi> 33.4. God demands, <hi>What could have been done more?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 5.</note> as if he would have been better to us, had we been better to our own ſelves.
<q>
                  <l>Sed nos per noſtrum, non patimur ſcelus</l>
                  <l>Iracundo Deum ponere fulmina.</l>
               </q> Sinners ſtanding out againſt all admonitions, weave the web of their owne ruine, and are the unhappy Artificers of their own deſtruction; <hi>Julian</hi> gave for his Armes in his Eſcutcheon an Eagle ſtruck through the heart, with a flight Shaft feathered out of her own wings, with this Motto:
<q>—Propriis configimur alis.</q>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:118728:11"/>A perfect Embleme of depraved man. Our Death flyes to us with our owne wings, and our owne Feathers pierce us to the heart: <hi>Perditio tua ex te, O Iſrael; thou haſt deſtroyed thy ſelfe, O Iſrael:</hi> we muſt ſay with <hi>Jeruſaleus, The Lord is righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous, but we have rebelled againſt him;</hi> which may ſerve as the ſecond <hi>Reaſon</hi> for confirmation of the <hi>Doctrine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Ad vindictam acuendam,</hi> when theſe diſtributions of favours prevaile nothing but to encourage and harden men in their ſinnes: it exaſperates judgement, and ſharpens re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge againſt them. <hi>Laeſa patientia fit furor,</hi> Love neglected, turnes into the moſt deſperate Hatred, as the ſweeteſt Wines make the tarteſt Vinegar: The more bonds of Duty, the more Plagues for neglect: This was it which aggravated <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raels</hi> ſinne, that God had known her of all the Families of the Earth, therefore he would ſurely puniſh her for all her ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities, <hi>Amos</hi> 3.2. When wiſdome had made her unſucceſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full addreſſes to the world, in the firſt Chapter of the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verbs,</hi> when her warnings were all ſlighted, her invitations neglected, as if her eyes had flaſhed like Lightning, her voice ecchoes and reſounds like Thunder; <hi>Becauſe I have called and ye refuſed, I have ſtretched out mine hand, and no man regar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded; but ye have ſet at nought all my Counſell, and would have none of my reproofe, I will laugh at your calamity, and mock when your feare cometh;</hi> and to the end of the Chapter, ſhe goes on enraged with an holy fury; which things being premiſed; I ſhall give you one or two inferences, with which I ſhall put a period to my preſent employment.</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>Gratitudinem ſuadet,</hi> It ſtrongly obligeth us to grate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full returnes of Prayers, and Praiſes: God though he hath put a cup of affliction into our hands, yet is it ſweetned with ſome ingredients of <hi>Mercy;</hi> though he hath fed us with bread of <hi>Adverſity,</hi> and waters of <hi>Affliction,</hi> yet are not our teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers removed into Corners, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 30.20. we need not with <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie</hi>'s Daughter, name <hi>England, Ichabod,</hi> the <hi>Arke</hi> and glory of the <hi>Lord</hi> is not as yet, God be thanked, taken away from us. Even amidſt the neighing of Horſes, and ratling of Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour, amidſt the ſound of the Drums and Trumpets, ſtill have we thoſe who blow the Trumpet in <hi>Sion,</hi> and ſound an alarum
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:118728:12"/>upon Gods holy Mountaine. Speak O Son! whether in all thy travels from <hi>Eaſt</hi> to <hi>Weſt,</hi> from one quarter of the <hi>Heaven,</hi> even to the other, did thine eyes behold ſuch an illightned <hi>Goſhen,</hi> bleſſed with the number of Gods Embaſſadors, faithfully diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charging their Miniſteriall duties? let us therefore labour to live anſwerably and proportionably to this <hi>Mercy,</hi> let us walk as becometh the Goſpell. It is ſtoried of <hi>Marcus Manlius,</hi> having deſerved well of the <hi>Roman</hi> ſtate for defending the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitoll, afterwards upon occaſion, fell into disfavour with the people, was adjudged to death; however, their gratitude prompted them ſo farre, as that they would not execute him in any place, from whence they might diſcover any part of the Capitoll: at laſt in the <hi>Peteline</hi> Grove, from whence no Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacle of that Edifice could be diſcerned, he was put to death; It is a wonder men can finde any corner to ſinne in, any place to let looſe the reines to a licentious exorbitancy, eſpecially ſince which way ſoever men turne their eyes, they meet with ſome ſignall objects of Divine favour, and ſhould be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagements to ſtop and check us in our full carriere of ſinning: nay yet more, to take up the Prophets <hi>Hallelujah; O enter into his gates with thanksgiving, and into his Courts with praiſe, be thankefull unto him, and speak good of his name; For the Lord is gracious,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, (though many more might have been added) <hi>excitet induſtriam,</hi> let theſe premonitions have what they chiefly call for, and that is our amendment and reformation,
<q>Diſcite juſtitiam moniti non temnere divos.</q> Sure I am, every one of us, have had our hands in pulling down judgments, we are therefore deeply concerned to prevent them for the future: From the higheſt to the loweſt, we have contributed our Talent, and caſt in our Oyle to encreaſe the flames: Let us at laſt after ſo many warnings ſhot off from Heaven, bring our buckets to extinguiſh them. To what pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe thinke you is it that God all this while hath not ſtopt the mouths of his <hi>Harbingers,</hi> nor yet cancelled their Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on? Theſe Olive-branches in their Mouths, are reall invita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:118728:12"/>to reconciliation: We wooe, and we wooe, we entreat, and we threat, and all <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and will neither move or conquer us?</p>
            <p>I believe there is none ſuch a ſtranger in our <hi>Iſrael,</hi> but knowes how it fareth with us, and that the time is come, that <hi>God ariſe and have Mercy upon us, yea the time is come: For why her Servants thinke upon her ſtones, and it pittieth them to ſee her lying in the Dust.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That which remaineth for us to performe, is, that we entreat Almighty God, that being taught by his Word, and admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed by his Rod, and humbled under his correcting hand, we ſhould flye to his <hi>Mercy,</hi> acknowledge his <hi>Juſtice,</hi> implore his <hi>Favour,</hi> for the pardon of our <hi>Sinnes,</hi> for the amendment of our <hi>Lives,</hi> and for the Salvation of our <hi>Souls,</hi> and all for the merits and mediation of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt the Righteous:</hi> To whom with the <hi>Father,</hi> and the <hi>Holy Ghoſt,</hi> be all Honour and Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, Praiſe, Power, Might, Majeſty, Dignity and Dominion aſcribed. <hi>Amen, Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
